Contact

Name: Sumana Bhlapibul

Email: mailto:sumana.bhlapibul@outlook.com

Mobile: +31 6 52067057

Nationality: Dutch

Website:

https://sumanabhlapibul.github.io/SumAnalytics/

Summary

I am a chemical engineer with strong business background and extensive experience in data and information management. I help business gain insights from their data and feel rewarding when the business can make smarter decision.

I have many tools in my toolbox. My preferred tools for data science are spreadsheet, python, Power BI and SQL.

Who I am



Education & Courses

- 1983 Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, Thailand Chemical Engineering
- 1990 University of Ulster, Northern Ireland, UK MBA (International Business and Industrial Development)
- 1995 Charter Institute of Purchasing and Supply, UK MCIPS (Corporate Member Charter Institute of Purchasing and Supply)
- 2006 PRINCE2 Project Management
- 2018 Microsoft Professional Program : Data Science, Al, Big Data, IoT, DevOps
- 2019 IBM Data Science

Language

Thai Mother language

English Fluent Dutch Good



Sumana Bhlapibul

Work Experience

2023 Freelance Consultant & Data Scientist SumAnalytics

2018- 2022 Data Science Coach & Developer
The Do Good Only Company BV

2014 – 2018 Independent Study, Adventure Travel

and Home Management

2011 – 2014 Business Process and IT Manager Gate terminal B.V.

I was responsible for the overall IT of the new LNG terminal at the Maasvlakte. I managed, guarded and executed efficient and effective daily and long term continuity of the business process and the industrial & office IT environment.

2001-2010 Senior Supply Chain Consultant Shell Global Solutions International

I helped refineries and petrochemical plants to improve their bottom line profit by improving their supply planning and scheduling process, hydrocarbon management and plant information management

1993-2001 Procurement & Contract Supervisor, Lead Process Engineer Shell operating company

I worked in teams that designed, built, started-up and operated a refinery. My roles included

- Reviewed a grass root refinery conceptual design and its feasibility study
- material procurement during Engineering Procurement and Construction phase
- set up a contracting department during the start up phase and
- supported the refinery operation as process engineer in the operational phase.
- Supervised and trained process engineers
- Initiated , Led, Designed various plant improvement projects
- Designed interconnection piping synergy between 2 complex refineries i.e. Hydrocracker refinery & Catalytic Cracker Refinery

1983-1993 Procurement
Petroleum Authority of Thailand & Thai Petrochemical Industry

I analyzed world market, evaluated crude, petrochemical feedstock and petroleum product prices, negotiated and finalized purchasing contracts

Credentials

Data Science and Data Analysis

- Microsoft Al
- Microsoft Data Science
- Microsoft Big Data
- Microsoft Data Analysis
- Microsoft IoT
- Microsoft DevOps
- Google Data Analytics
- IBM Data Science
- IBM Data Analysis and Visualization
- IBM Applied Data Science
- DataCamp Data Science with Python
- Harvard X Using python for Research
- Full Stack web development with Angular
- Google Data Analytics
- Datacamp Data Science
- Coursera HTML, CSS, and Javascript for Web Developers

•

Others

- PRINCE2 (Project Management Practitioner)
- PRINCE2 (Project Management Foundation)
- .Net Web Development Certified Professional
- International Trading and Risk Management
- Qualified ISO 9000 internal audit
- Qualified instructor for Quality and Customer Focus
- VCA Basic Elements of Safety

Applications & Tools

Programming - python, R, C#

Office—MS Excel, Word , Power Point, Project

Drawing - MS Visio

Database - MS Access, SQL Server, Oracle

Reporting Tool - Business Object

Data Historian - Exaquantum, PI

Development - VB.Net, VBA, Blazor

Document Management System - Livelink, SharePoint

Web Development - HTML, CSS, JS, Blazor, Angular, C#,

Wordpress

Presentation, Whitepaper and Trainings provided

I wrote various technical papers and gave training to internal and external customer's e.g.

- Refinery mass balance and vertical integration white paper
- Volatile Organic Compound VOC emission white paper
- Project Management (PRINCE II and PMBOK) Training
- Data Integration Training
- Supply Chain Vertical Integration Training & Paper